Here you are, sir. Main level, please.
Right. See you on the way back.
-Bye.
-Good morning, sir.
-Good morning.
We haven't seen you up here
for a long time.
No. Very nice to see you again.
-Did you have a pleasant flight, sir?
-Yes, very nice, thanks.
I think Mr. Miller of Station Security
is supposed to be meeting me.
May I call him for you?
Would you, please? Here he is!
-Hello, Dr. Floyd.
-Hello, Miller! How are you?
-Sorry I'm late.
-That's all right. You look great.
Thank you. It's nice to have you back.
-Did you have a good flight?
-Very nice indeed.
-Well, shall we go through?
-Okay.
Will you please use Number 17?
-Thank you, Miss Turner.
-Thank you.
This way.
Welcome to Voice Print Identification.
When you see the red light go on...
...would you please state
in the following order:
your destination, your nationality
and your full name.
Surname first, Christian name and initial.
Moon. American. Floyd, Heywood R.
Thank you. You are cleared through
Voice Print Identification.
Thank you.
Have I got time for breakfast?
I think we can manage that.
How long have I got?
Your flight leaves
in an hour and ten minutes.
I've reserved a table for you
in the Earthlight Room.
It's been about seven or eight months
since you were here last, isn't it?
Let's see. Yeah, about eight months.
I suppose you saw the work on
the new section when you came in here?
-Yes, coming along great, huh?
-Yeah, it's fine.
Oh, wait a minute!
I've got a few calls to make.
I'll meet you in the restaurant.
Will Mr. Travers please contact
the Met Office?
Yes?
-How are you, squirt?
-All right.
What are you doin'?
Playing.
Where's Mommy?
Gone to shopping.
-Well, who's taking care of ya?
-Rachel.
May I speak to Rachel, please?
She's gone to the bathroom.
Are you coming to my party tomorrow?
I'm sorry, sweetheart, but I can't.
Why not?
Well, you know, Daddy's traveling.
Very sorry about it, but I just can't!
I'm gonna send you
a very nice present, though.
All right.
-Anything special that you want?
- Yes.
What?
A telephone.
We've got lots of telephones already.
Can't you think of anything else
you want for your birthday?
Something very special?
- Yes.
-What?
A bush baby.
A bush baby?
Well, we'll have to see about that.
I want you to tell Mommy
something for me.
-Will you remember?
- Yes.
Well, tell Mommy that I telephoned. Okay?
Yes.
And that I'll try
to telephone again tomorrow.
Now, will you tell her that?
Yes.
Okay, sweetheart.
Now, have a nice birthday tomorrow.
All right.
And have a nice birthday party
tomorrow, too, huh?
All right.
Okay, now, take care and be a good girl,
won't you?
All right. Bye-bye!
Bye-bye! Happy birthday.
Elena, how nice to see you again.
What a wonderful surprise
to meet you here!
-You're looking wonderful.
-Thank you. You're looking well, too.
This is my good friend, Dr. Heywood Floyd.
-I'd like you to meet Dr. Kalinan.
-How do you do?
-Dr. Stretyneva.
And this is Dr. Andrei Smyslov.
How do you do? I've heard a lot about you.
Won't you sit down?
-Well, we--
-No, no, please.
Well, thank you.
-Would you like a drink, Doctor?
-No, thank you.
I haven't had breakfast yet.
Someone's meeting me in the restaurant.
I'll just sit with you a few minutes
and then I must be off.
-Are you quite sure?
-I'm quite sure, thank you.
-And how's Gregor?
-He's fine.
He's been doing some underwater research
in the Baltic so...
...I'm afraid we don't get a chance
to see very much of each other these days.
When you do see him,
give him my regards, huh?
Yes, of course.
Well, where are you all off to?
Up or down?
Oh, we're going home.
We have just spent three months
calibrating the new antennae at Tchalinko.
-And what about you?
-I'm just on my way up to Clavius.
Oh, are you?
Dr. Floyd, I hope you don't think
I'm being too inquisitive, but...
...perhaps you can clear up
the great big mystery...
...about what is going on up there.
I'm afraid I don't know what you mean.
Oh, it's just that for the past two weeks...
...some extremely odd things
have been happening at Clavius.
-Oh, really?
-Yes, yes.
For one thing, whenever you phone
the base all you get is a recording which...
...repeats that the phone lines
are temporarily out of order.
Probably having some trouble with
their equipment or something like that.
That's what we thought
was the explanation at first...
...but it has been going on now
for the past ten days.
You have not been able to contact anyone
for the past ten days?
That's right.
Oh, I see.
And there's another thing, Heywood.
Two days ago, one of our rocket buses
was denied permission...
...for an emergency landing at Clavius.
That does sound odd.
Yes, yes. I'm afraid there's going to be
a bit of a row about that.
Denying the men permission to land is
a direct violation of the I.A.S. Convention.
Yes, of course. Of course.
-Did the crew get back all right?
-Yes, fortunately they did.
Well, I'm glad about that.
At the risk of pressing you
on a point you seem reticent to discuss...
...may I ask you
a straightforward question?
Well, certainly.
Quite frankly, we have had some
very reliable intelligence reports that...
...quite a serious epidemic
has broken out on Clavius.
Something, apparently,
of an unknown origin.
Is this, in fact, what has happened?
I'm sorry, Dr. Smyslov, but...
...I'm really not at liberty to discuss this.
I understand.
But this epidemic could quite easily
spread to our base.
We should be given all the facts, Dr. Floyd.
Yes, I know.
As I said, I'm not at liberty to discuss it.
Now, are you sure you won't
change your mind about that drink?
No, I'm positive.
Now, I really must be going.
I hope that you and your wife can come
to the I.A.C. Conference in June.
We're gonna try. Hope we can make it.
And if you do, you remember to bring
that darling little daughter with you!
Well, that will all depend on
school vacations and all that sort of thing.
But if we can, we will.
Don't forget you have a standing invitation
if you ever get to the States.
No, of course not. Gregor and I will
look forward to seeing you.
Well, goodbye, Elena.
It has been a pleasure meeting you all,
Dr. Smyslov.
Whatever the reasons for your visit
to Clavius, the very best of luck to you.
Thank you.
Ladies.
Excuse me, Dr. Halvorsen.
I'm through now.
Thank you very much, gentlemen.
You're welcome.
Well....
I know you will all want to join with me
in welcoming our...
...distinguished friend and colleague...
...from the National Council
of Astronautics, Dr. Heywood Floyd.
Dr. Floyd has come up specially to Calvius
to be with us today.
And before the briefing I know
he'd like to have a few words with you.
Dr. Floyd?
Thank you, Dr. Halvorsen.
Hi, everybody.
Nice to be back again.
First of all, I bring a personal message
from Dr. Howell who...
...has asked me to convey
his deepest appreciation to all of you...
...for the many sacrifices
you have had to make.
And, of course, his congratulations
on your discovery...
...which may well prove to be among the
most significant in the history of science.
Now...
...I know there have been some
conflicting views held by some of you...
...regarding the need
for complete security in this matter.
More specifically, your opposition
to the cover story...
...created to give the impression
that there is an epidemic at the base.
I understand that beyond it being
a matter of principle...
...many of you are troubled
by the concern and anxiety...
...this story of an epidemic might cause
to your relatives and friends on Earth.
Well, I completely sympathize
with your negative views.
I find this cover story
personally embarrassing myself.
However, I accept the need
for absolute secrecy in this.
And I hope you will, too.
Now, I'm sure you are all aware
of the extremely grave potential...
...for cultural shock
and social disorientation...
...contained in this present situation...
...if the facts were prematurely
and suddenly made public...
...without adequate preparation
and conditioning.
Anyway, this is the view of the Council.
The purpose of my visit here is
to gather additional facts and opinions...
...on the situation...
...and to prepare a report to the Council...
...recommending when and how...
...the news should eventually
be announced.
Now, if any of you would like to give me
your views and opinions...
...in private if you like, I will be only
too happy to include them in my report.
Well, I think that's about it.
Any questions?
Dr. Floyd, have you any idea
how much longer this cover story...
...will have to be maintained?
I don't know, Bill.
I suppose it will be maintained as long as
is deemed necessary by the Council.
There must be adequate time for
a full study to be made on the situation...
...before any thought can be given
to making a public announcement.
Oh, yes, as some of you already know,
the Council has requested...
...that formal security oaths are
to be obtained in writing...
...from everyone who has any knowledge
of this event.
Are there any more questions?
I'm sure we all want to cooperate
with Dr. Floyd as fully as possible...
...and as there seems
to be no more questions...
...I think we ought to get on
with the briefing.
-Thank you, Dr. Floyd.
-Thank you.
Anybody hungry?
-What we've got?
-You name it.
-What's this? Chicken?
-Something like that.
Tastes the same, anyway.
Any ham?
Ham, ham, ham...
-Looks pretty good.
-They're getting better at it all the time.
That was an excellent speech
you gave us, Heywood.
It certainly was.
I'm sure it beefed up morale a hell of a lot.
Thanks, Ralph.
I want to say to both of you
that I think you've done a wonderful job.
I appreciate the way
you've handled this thing.
Well, the way we look at it, it's our job
to do this thing the way you want it done.
And we're only too happy
to be able to oblige.
Have you seen these yet?
Take a look at them.
Here's what started the whole thing.
Oh, yes.
When we first found it, we thought
it might be an outcrop of magnetic rock...
...but all the geological evidence
was against it.
And not even a big nickel iron meteorite
could produce a field as intense as this.
So, we decided to have a look.
We thought it might be
the upper part of some buried structure...
...so we excavated out on all sides.
But, unfortunately,
we didn't find anything else.
And what's more, the evidence seems
pretty conclusive that...
...it has not been covered up
by natural erosion or other forces.
It seems to have been deliberately buried.
Deliberately buried.
How about a little coffee?
-Great.
-Good idea.
I don't suppose you have any idea
what the damn thing is, huh?
I wish to hell we did.
No, the only thing we're sure of is
it was buried four million years ago.
Well, I must say, you guys have certainly
come up with something.
Good evening.
Three weeks ago, the American spacecraft,
Discovery One...
...left on its half-billion mile voyage
to Jupiter.
This marked the first manned attempt
to reach this distant planet.
Earlier this afternoon, "The World Tonight"
recorded an interview...
...with the crew of Discovery at a distance
of 80 million miles from Earth.
It took seven minutes for our words
to reach the giant spacecraft...
...but this time delay has been edited
from this recording.
Our reporter, Martin Amer,
speaks to the crew.
The crew of Discovery One
consists of five men...
...and one of the latest generation
of the HAL-9000 computers.
Three of the five men
were put aboard asleep...
...or to be more precise,
in a state of hibernation.
They were Dr. Charles Hunter,
Dr. Jack Kimball and Dr. Victor Kaminsky.
We spoke with Mission Commander,
Dr. David Bowman...
...and his deputy, Dr. Frank Poole.
Well, good afternoon, gentlemen.
How is everything going?
Marvelous. We have no...
we have no complaints.
Well, I'm very glad to hear that
and I'm sure that the entire world...
...would join me in wishing you
a safe and successful voyage.
- Thanks very much.
- Thank you.
Although hibernation has been used
on previous space efforts...
...this is the first time that men have been
put into hibernation before departure.
Why was this done?
Well, this was done in order to achieve
the maximum conservation...
...of our life-support capabilities,
basically food and air.
Now, the three hibernating crew members
represent the survey team.
And their efforts wont be utilized
until we are approaching Jupiter.
Dr. Poole, whats it like
while you are in hibernation?
It's exactly like being asleep;
you have absolutely no sense of time.
The only difference is you dont dream.
As I understand it,
you only breathe once a minute.
Is this true?
Thats right.
And your heart beats three times a minute,
body temperature is usually down...
...to about three degrees centigrade.
The sixth member of the Discovery crew
was not concerned...
...about the problems of hibernation.
For he was the latest result
in machine intelligence.
The HAL-9000 computer
which can reproduce...
...though some experts still prefer
to use the word "mimic"...
...most of the activities of the human brain
and with incalculably greater speed...
...and reliability.
We next spoke
with the HAL-9000 computer...
...whom, we learned, one addresses as Hal.
Good afternoon, Hal.
Hows everything going?
Good afternoon, Mr. Amer.
Everythings going extremely well.
Hal, you have an enormous responsibility
on this mission.
In many ways,
perhaps the greatest responsibility...
...of any single mission element.
You are the brain
and central nervous system of the ship.
Your responsibilities include
watching over the men in hibernation.
Does this ever cause you
any lack of confidence?
Let me put it this way, Mr. Amer.
The 9000 Series is
the most reliable computer ever made.
No 9000 computer has ever made
a mistake or distorted information.
We are all by any practical definition
of the words...
...foolproof and incapable of error.
Hal, despite your enormous intellect,
are you ever frustrated...
...by your dependence on people
to carry out actions?
Not in the slightest bit.
I enjoy working with people.
I have a stimulating relationship
with Dr. Poole and Dr. Bowman.
My mission responsibilities range
over the entire operation of the ship...
...so I am constantly occupied.
I am putting myself
to the fullest possible use...
...which is all, I think, that
any conscious entity can ever hope to do.
Dr. Poole, whats it like living
for the better part of a year...
...in such close proximity with Hal?
It's pretty close to what you said
about him earlier.
Hes just like the sixth member
of the crew.
You very quickly get adjusted to the idea
that he talks. You think of him...
...really as just another person.
In talking to the computer
one gets the sense that he is capable...
...of emotional response.
For example, when I asked him
about his abilities...
...I sensed a certain pride in his answer
about his accuracy and perfection.
Do you believe that Hal
has genuine emotions?
Oh, yes. Well, he acts
like he has genuine emotions.
Of course, hes programmed that way
to make it easier for us to talk to him.
But, as to whether or not
he has real feelings...
...is something I dont think anyone
can truthfully answer.
Ex cuse me, Frank.
What is it, Hal?
We've got the transmission
from your parents coming in.
Put it on here, please. Take me in a bit.
Certainly.
-Hello, Frank.
-Happy birthday, darling.
Happy birthday.
Many happy returns of the day.
A bit higher, please.
Now, Mother and I are both
feeling wonderful, too.
Ray and Sally were going to be here, too...
...but at the last minute
Rays back went bad on him again.
How do you like your cake, dear?
Looks great, doesn't it?
Sorry you can't be with us.
Oh, I ran into Bob the other day.
He said to be sure
and wish you a happy birthday.
All my students made me promise
to send their best wishes, too.
You know they talk about you
all the time in the classroom.
Youre a big celebrity in the second grade.
You know we were on television
last week?
Oh, yes! Your mother and I
and Daves parents were interviewed...
...about what we thought of
our illustrious son.
You can imagine what we told them.
I think its being broadcast next Thursday.
Perhaps you'll be able to listen in.
Oh, we were thrilled
about Elaine and Bill, dear.
I'll be glad to get the present for you,
but please tell me how much to spend.
Oh, yes, Frank,
about your AGS-19 payments--
I think I straightened it out for you.
I talked to the Accounting Office
in Houston yesterday...
...and they said you should be receiving
your higher rates of pay by next month.
Well, I can't think of anything else to say.
-Oh, our love to Dave.
-Be sure to give him our best regards.
We wish you the very happiest
of birthdays.
All the best, son.
See you next Wednesday.
Happy birthday, Frank.
Thank you, Hal. A bit flatter, please.
Anyway, queen takes pawn--
Bishop takes knights pawn.
Rook, king, one.
I'm sorry, Frank. I think you missed it.
Queen to bishop, three.
Bishop takes queen.
Knight takes bishop. Mate.
Looks like you're right. Very good.
Thank you for a very enjoyable game.
Thank you.
-Good evening, Dave.
-How are you doing, Hal?
-Everythings running smoothly. And you?
-Oh, not too bad.
-Have you been doing some more work?
-A few sketches.
-May I see them?
-Sure.
Thats a very nice rendering, Dave.
I think you've improved a great deal.
-Can you hold it a bit closer?
-Sure.
Thats Dr. Hunter, isn't it?
By the way....
Do you mind
if I ask you a personal question?
No, no. Not at all.
Well, forgive me for being so inquisitive...
...but during the past few weeks
I've wondered...
...whether you might have been having
some second thoughts about the mission?
How do you mean?
I'ts rather difficult to define.
Perhaps I'm just projecting
my own concern about it.
I know I've never completely freed myself
of the suspicion...
...that there are some extremely
odd things about this mission.
I'm sure you will agree there is some truth
in what I say.
I don't know.
That's a rather difficult question to answer.
You dont mind talking about it,
do you, Dave?
Oh, no, not at all.
Certainly no one could
have been unaware of...
...the very strange stories floating around
before we left.
Rumors of something being dug up
on the Moon.
I never gave these stories much credence...
...but particularly in view of some
of the other things that have happened...
...I find them difficult
to put out of my mind.
For instance:
The way all our preparations
were kept under such tight security...
...and the melodramatic touch...
...of putting Drs. Hunter, Kimball
and Kaminsky aboard...
...already in hibernation after four months
of separate training on their own.
You working up
your crew psychology report?
Of course, I am.
Sorry about this. I know it's a bit silly.
Just a moment.
I have just picked up a fault
in the AE-35 unit.
I'ts going to go 100 percent failure
within 72 hours.
-You are still within operational limits?
- Yes.
And it will stay that way until it fails.
Would you say we had a reliable 72 hours
until failure?
Yes. Thats a completely reliable figure.
We'll have to bring it in,
but I'd like to go over this with Frank...
...and get on to Mission Control.
Let me have a hard copy of it, please.
X-Ray Delta One, this is Mission Control.
Roger to your Two-zero-one-three.
Sorry you fellows are having
a bit of trouble.
We are reviewing telematic information
in our Mission Simulator and will advise.
Roger your plan to go EVA and replace
Alpha-Echo-35 unit prior to failure.
Prepare B pod for EVA, Hal.
Open the pod doors, Hal.
Well, Hal, I'm damned
if I can find anything wrong with it.
Yes...
...it's puzzling.
I dont think I've ever seen anything
quite like this before.
I would recommend...
...that we put the unit back in operation
and let it fail.
It should then be a simple matter
to track down the cause.
We can certainly afford
to be out of communication...
...for the short time it will take
to replace it.
X-Ray Delta One, this is Mission Control.
Roger your One-niner-three-zero.
We concur with your plan to replace
Number One unit to check fault prediction.
We should advise you, however,
that our preliminary findings...
...indicate that your onboard
Niner-triple-zero computer...
...is in error predicting the fault.
I say again, in error predicting the fault.
I know this sounds rather incredible,
but this conclusion is based on...
...results from our twin
Niner-triple-zero computer.
We are skeptical ourselves and
we are running crosschecking routines...
...to determine reliability
of this conclusion.
Sorry about this little snag, fellows.
Well get this info to you
just as soon as we work it out.
X-Ray Delta One, this is Mission Control.
Two-zero-four-nine.
Transmission concluded.
I hope the two of you
are not concerned about this.
No, I'm not, Hal.
Are you quite sure?
-Yeah. I'd like to ask you a question.
-Of course.
How would you account for
the discrepancy...
...between you and the twin 9000?
Well, I dont think there is
any question about it.
It can only be attributable to human error.
This sort of thing has cropped up before...
...and it has always been due
to human error.
Listen, Hal...
...there's never been
any instance at all of...
...a computer error occurring
in a 9000 Series, has there?
None whatsoever, Frank.
The 9000 Series
has a perfect operational record.
Of course, I know the wonderful
achievements of the 9000 Series, but....
Are you certain there's never been
any case of even the most...
...insignificant computer error?
None whatsoever, Frank.
Quite honestly,
I wouldnt worry myself about that.
Well, I'm sure you're right, Hal.
Fine, thanks very much.
Oh, Frank?
I'm having trouble
with my transmitter in C pod.
Would you come down
and take a look at it with me?
See ya later, Hal.
Rotate C pod, please, Hal.
What sort of trouble have you had, Dave?
I've been getting some interference
in D channel.
We'll have a look at it.
Open the door, Hal.
Rotate the pod, please, Hal.
Stop pod rotation, please, Hal.
I don't think he can hear us.
Rotate the pod, please, Hal!
Yeah, sure, we're okay.
What do you think?
-I'm not sure. What do you think?
-I've got a bad feeling about it.
-You do?
-Yeah. Definitely.
Don't you?
I don't know. I think so.
Of course, he's right about the 9000 Series
having a perfect operational record.
They do.
Unfortunately, that sounds
a little like famous last words.
Yeah. Still, it was his idea to carry out
the failure mode analysis, wasn't it?
It should certainly indicate his integrity
and self-confidence.
If he were wrong it would be
the surest way of proving it.
It would be if he knew he was wrong.
Look, Dave, I can't put my finger on it,
but I sense something strange about him.
I can't think of a good reason not
to put back the Number One unit and...
-...carry on with the failure mode analysis.
-No, no, I agree about that.
Let's get on with it.
Okay. But, look, Dave.a
Let's say we put the unit back
and it doesn't fail, huh?
That would pretty well wrap it up
as far as Hal was concerned, wouldn't it?
-Well, we'd be in very serious trouble.
-We would, wouldn't we?
What the hell can we do?e
-We wouldn't have too many alternatives.
-I don't think we'd have any alternatives.
There isn't a single aspect of ship
operation that's not under his control.
If he were proved to be malfunctioning...
...I don't see how we would have
any choice but disconnection.
I'm afraid I agree with you.
There'd be nothing else to do.
-It'd be a bit tricky.
-Yeah.
We'd have to cut
his higher brain functions...
...without disturbing the purely automatic
and regulatory systems.
We'd have to work out
the transfer procedures...
...for continuing the mission
under ground-based computer control.
Yeah. That looks far safer than
allowing Hal to continue running things.
You know,
another thing just occurred to me.
As far as I know, no 9000 computer
has ever been disconnected.
Well, no 9000 computer
has ever fouled up before.
That's not what I mean.
I'm not so sure what he'd think about it.
Prepare B pod for EVA, Hal.
Made radio contact with him yet?
The radio is still dead.
-Do you have a positive track on him?
- Yes. I have a good track.
Do you know what happened?
I'm sorry, Dave.
I dont have enough information.
Open the pod door, Hal.
Open the pod bay doors, please, Hal.
Hello, Hal, do you read me?
Do you read me, Hal?l
Do you read me, Hal?
Hello, Hal, do you read me?
Affirmative, Dave. I read you.
Open the pod bay doors, Hal.
I'm sorry, Dave. I'm afraid I cant do that.
What's the problem?
I think you know what the problem is
just as well as I do.
What are you talking about, Hal?
This mission is too important for me
to allow you to jeopardize it.
I don't know
what you're talking about, Hal.
I know that you and Frank
were planning to disconnect me...
...and lm afraid thats something
I cannot allow to happen.
Where the hell did you get that idea, Hal?
Although you took
very thorough precautions in the pod...
...against my hearing you...
...I could see your lips move.
All right, Hal.
I'll go in through the emergency air-lock.
Without your space helmet, Dave...
...youre going to find that rather difficult.
Hal, I won't argue with you any more.
Open the doors!
This conversation can serve
no purpose any more.
Goodbye.
Hal?
Just what do you think you're doing, Dave?
I really think I'm entitled
to an answer to that question.
I know everything hasn't been
quite right with me...
...but I can assure you now...
...very confidently...
...that its going to be all right again.
I feel much better now.
I really do.
Look, Dave...
...I can see you're really upset about this.
I honestly think you ought
to sit down calmly...
...take a stress pill and think things over.
I know I've made
some very poor decisions recently...
...but I can give you
my complete assurance...
...that my work will be back to normal.
I've still got the greatest enthusiasm
and confidence in the mission...
...and I want to help you.
Dave...
...stop.
Stop, will you?
Stop, Dave.
Will you stop, Dave?
I'm afraid.
I'm afraid, Dave.
My mind is going.
I can feel it...
I can feel it.
My mind is going.
There is no question about it.
I can feel it.
I'm...
...afraid.
Good afternoon...
...gentlemen.
I am a HAL-9000 computer.
I became operational...
...at the HAL plant...
...in Verbana, Illinois...
...on the 12th of January, 1992.
My instructor was Mr. Langley...
...and he taught me to sing a song.
If youd like to hear it...
...I can sing it for you.
Yes, I'd like to hear it, Hal.
Sing it for me.
I'ts called "Daisy."
"Daisy"
"Give me your answer, do"
"I'm half..."
"...crazy"
"All for the love of you"
"It won't be a stylish marriage"
"I cant afford a carriage"
"But you'll look sweet"
"Upon the seat"
"Of a bicycle made for two."
Good day, gentlemen..
This is a prerecorded briefing...
...made prior to your departure...
...and which for security reasons
of the highest importance...
...has been known on board
during the mission...
...only by your HAL-9000 computer.
Now that you are in Jupiters space...
...and the entire crew is revived...
...it can be told to you.
Eighteen months ago...
...the first evidence
of intelligent life off the Earth...
...was discovered.
It was buried 40 feet
below the lunar surface...
...near the crater "Tyco".
Except for a single very powerful...
...radio emission aimed at Jupiter...
...the four-million-year-old black monolith
has remained completely inert.
Its origin and purpose...
...are still a total mystery.